When you hear the phrase, technical documentation,
عندما تسمع العبارة، الوثائق التقنية،
you might think of dry literature that's difficult to understand.
قد تفكر في الأدب الجامد الذي يصعب فهمه.
But good documentation isn't boring or unapproachable.
لكن الوثائق الجيدة ليست مملة أو غير قابلة للتصديق.
Often it's written in plain English.
وكثيرًا ما تكتب باللغة الإنجليزية البسيطة.
Sometimes it's even written as a series of guides or tutorials.
في بعض الأحيان تكتب على شكل سلسلة من الأدلة أو الدروس.
As it turns out, there isn't a secret ruling body that makes laws for
كما اتضح، ليس هناك هيئة حكم سرية تُعد القوانين
what documentation should and shouldn't look like.
لما ينبغي أن تبدو عليه الوثائق وما لا ينبغي.
That's because, unlike your code, which is written for
هذا لأنه، على عكس الكود، الذي يُكتب لأجهزة الكمبيوتر،
computers, documentation is written for humans.
تتم كتابة الوثائق من أجل البشر.
Documentation exists to help us make sense of the code that we've written,
توجد الوثائق من أجل مساعدتنا في استنباط المعلومات عن الكود الذي نكتبه.
which may not always be quite as intuitive as we'd like it to be.
وقد لا تكون الوثائق دائمًا بسيطة تمامًا كما نود أن يكون.
For instance, if you're working on a large open source library that other
على سبيل المثال، إذا كنت تعمل على مكتبة كبيرة مفتوحة المصدر يمكن لأشخاص آخرين استخدامها،
people can use, good documentation is absolutely essential for
فإن الوثائق الجيدة ضرورية جدًا
acquiring both users and contributors.
للحصول على كل من المستخدمين والمساهمين.
If your documentation is good,
إذا كانت وثائقك جيدة،
people will want to use your library in their projects.
فسيحتاج الأشخاص إلى استخدام مكتبتك في مشاريعهم.
If your documentation is great,
إذا كانت وثائقك كبيرة،
people might even chip in to help you with your library.
فمن الممكن أن يساهم الأشخاص في مساعدتك في مكتبتك.
Perhaps your project is a portfolio piece to help you land your first
ربما يكون مشروعك عبارة عن أعمال قائمة مشاريع تساعدك في إيجاد
job as a developer.
وظيفتك الأولى كمطور.
In that case, you want to document your work in a way an employer can
في هذه الحالة، تريد توثيق عملك بطريقة يمكن لصاحب العمل
easily skim and pull relevant information.
أن يستخلص المعلومات ذات الصلة ويحصل عليها بسهولة.
Give some thought as to who is going to be reading your documentation.
إعطاء بعض الاهتمام لمن سيقرأ وثائقك.
You won't always know who that is.
أنت لن تعرف دائمًا من يكون هذا.
You want it to be easy for
أنت تريد أن تكون سهلة
anyone to dive into your code and get it up and running.
لأي شخص يريد أن يتعرّف على الكود ويحصل عليه ويشغله.
With that in mind,
مع وضع ذلك في الاعتبار،
who do you think might be a potential end user of documentation?
من تعتقد سيكون المستخدم النهائي المحتمل للوثائق؟
Yourself, your coworkers, or your users?
نفسك أو زملائك في العمل أو المستخدمين؟